All right. Good morning. This is Dan Margulis filling in for Rabbi
Linzer while he's away. Today is the 10th of אדר Adar and
it is March 19th, 20th. I always miss a day with שבת
Shabbos because I don't think about the date. And we are going
to start on the bottom of ח עמוד ב. Chet Amud Beis.
I just wanted to make one mention to a תוספות ריד Tosafot
Rid from yesterday, very relevant to some of these questions we've had
about sort of the sarcastic refusal that suppose the man suggests to
the woman, "Here, be married to me with this 100 דינרים," dinars,
and she says, "Put it on a rock." So the תוספות ריד
Tosafot Rid on ח עמוד ב, Chet Amud Beis, he says, ואם
היה סלע שלה מקודשת. Ve'im haya sela shela mekudeshes. And the תוספות
ריד Tosafot Rid goes into this whole discussion about the psychology and
some of the sarcasm involved. So I think it's an important source
to take a look at later if you have the time, right
at the last תוספות ריד Tosafot Rid on ח עמוד ב. Chet
Amud Beis. I often,
when I've studied מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, which admittedly is not often
enough, I have found that the תוספות ריד Tosafot Rid is one
of my best friends moving forward. He has very creative and interesting
ideas and it's always worthwhile to take a look there just because
he has a different point of view.
But if the woman was given faith,
but she can do with the money was whatever she wants?
That's, of course, if it's her money, that's exactly the הוה אמינא
hava amina in the גמרא. Gemara.
But she can spend the money right away, I think. Of course,
why not?
What happens if that's the best way to demonstrate that she accepted?
If you get a divorce later?
So getting a divorce later has nothing to do with whether or
not she accepted to be married now.
He don't get back anymore the money. He wouldn't get back the
money, that's correct.
So and obviously the קידושין Kiddushin money...
If you give a girl a ring,
then
you break up, she would not give back the ring.
Well, it depends, you know, what we talk about now with engagement
rings and things like that doesn't necessarily have such a clear הלכה
halakha basis. We'll see a little bit about it today in the
גמרא Gemara actually, but certainly the money given for קידושין Kiddushin is
understood very clearly to be a full, wholehearted gift to the woman
even if the marriage ends up breaking off.
She invested it in property for both?
Well, that would be a good idea too. Okay, so let's start
just from the last few lines of ח עמוד ב. Chet Amud
Beis. We had just talked about the case where the dog was
chasing after the woman and she suggested to the man, "Give the
bread to the dog in order to distract the dog so the
dog does not bite her," and that case was left as a
תיקו teiku by רב מרי. Rav Mari. And now we have another
case: התקדשי לי בכיכר תנהו לעני. Hitkadshi li bekikar tenahu le'ani.
So the man says, "Be married to me with this loaf of
bread," and the woman says, "Give it to this poor person who's
sitting here." Okay. אינה מקודשת. Eina mekudeshes. She is not married to
him. אפילו עני הסמוך עליה, Afilu ani hasamuch aleha, even if it
is a poor person who regularly relies on צדקה tzedakah that she
gives him. Interesting to note that הלכה halakha does give a significance
to the fact that often the local poor of a community are
supported by particular people and that that often gives a sort of
a precedence or preference for who is going to be giving צדקה
tzedakah to that person and it's sort of almost considered to be
an obligation to a certain extent. And nonetheless, that is not considered
to be enough reason for it to be considered that she's accepting
the money from him to give to the poor person, rather that's
a way of rejecting it. אפילו עני הסמוך עליה, Afilu ani hasamuch
aleha, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמרה ליה כי היכי
דמחייבת ביה אנא הכי מחייבת ביה את. Amra leh ki heichi demichayavat
beih ana hachi michayavat beih at.
Just from the fact that I'm obligated myself to support
him, so too you're also obligated. Meaning, we each have the same
obligation to give צדקה. tzedakah. The fact that I'm asking you, the
fact that she asks the man to give the bread to the
poor person means she's rejecting קידושין. Kiddushin. She's saying, "Just like I
support him, you should be supporting the poor also, don't get married
to me." So that's her way of rejecting it. ההוא גברא דהוה
קמזבין חומרי פתחיתא. Hahu gavra dehavah kamizban chumrei pitchita. There was a
man who was selling buttons or or some kind of trinkets. רש"י
Rashi says buttons.
It's an interesting piece of trivia, why did Napoleon lose in Russia?
It has to do with chemistry, that's why I know.
Napoleon's soldiers had tin buttons and when the temperature drops, tin goes
through a chemical change from one allotropic form to another and what's
called brittle tin or tin disease, when tin is exposed to cold
temperatures for a long time and the buttons fell off his army
jackets and they got cold, they froze because the jackets wouldn't close.
So it's just an interesting point, רש"י Rashi talks about בוטנין שעושין
של בדיל, butnin she'osin shel bedil, the first first רש"י Rashi on
ט עמוד א. Tet Amud Aleph. So if you make tin buttons,
which is very common, you can have some problems in the winter.
That is why it's cold in the room now.
That is why it is cold in this room now, exactly.
We'll talk about... Paying to free someone?
Paying to free someone? I mean to, you know, save someone's life.
Save someone's life.
Well, that was the case we ended with yesterday. Oh, so just
to say that there is a number of תוספות Tosafot in fact
that discuss that case exactly, which is that suppose there is a
possibility this is the case of are you obligated or if you
use someone else's money to save your own life, do you have
to pay it back or not? This is תוספות's Tosafot question because
תוספות Tosafot says look, I understand that we say יהרג ואל יעבור
Yehareg ve-al ya'avor about saving a life, right? Saving a person's life
is obviously supersedes basically every other מצוה mitzvah in the תורה Torah
except for
גילוי עריות, Giluy Arayot, שפיכות דמים, Shfichut Damim, and עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. So obviously stealing should be superseded by the need to save
your life. Do you pay it back? Do you pay it back?
Ah, so that's exactly the question. And that's a מחלוקת ראשונים, machloket
rishonim, which is that if you need to steal money in order
to save your life, for example, you know, the classic story, you
know, oh, would you steal a loaf of bread to save your
starving family? So in such a case, תוספות Tosafot at least entertains
the notion that maybe in such a case a person would actually
not need to pay back or perhaps you would need to pay
it back. It's just that you're פטור patur from the prohibition of
stealing, but that doesn't remove the monetary aspect of stealing or not.
So that's an extensive discussion in the ראשונים rishonim and אחרונים. acharonim.
But here, why would anyone say that you don't pay it back?
Because if the prohibition of theft has been overridden, then you're off
the hook. You needed this bread to survive. You needed the bread
to survive. Now you're not starving anymore. Okay, don't steal anymore. But
you wouldn't have any any financial obligation at that point. You're going
to ask somebody who was so poor they couldn't afford food that
now that they had to steal food and now how are they
even going to pay it back? So I think it's also two
different cases, right? One is a person who's in general very, very
poor and is starving to death or one is a case where
a person is, you know, needs a certain medication and tries to
steal the medication or something like that. That's a kind of a
different thing. There's a lot more to be said about that especially
in modern healthcare
healthcare climate to be talked about. Right. Well, exactly. We have to
continue with the דף, daf, it's an interesting question. Okay, so ההוא
גברא דהוה קזבין חמרי דפחתתא, hahu gavra dehavay kazavin chamrey de-pachtachta, he
was selling the the tin buttons. אתאי ההיא איתתא, Atay hahi iteta,
this woman came over to him. אמרה ליה, Amerah leh, she says
to him, הב לי חד שוכא, havli chad shuka, give me one
bead or one button. אמר לה, Amar lah, or one necklace of
the buttons perhaps. Okay, אמר לה, Amar lah, אי יהיבנא ליך מיקדשת
לי, ee havinah lach mekudeshet lee,
if I give it to you will you be married to me?
אמרה ליה, Amerah leh, הבא מהבא, hava me-hava, give it, give it,
with a double לשון. lashon. She just says give it to me.
Just give it to me.
So is that her saying 'Yes, I'm agreeing to marry you,' or
is it her saying 'I don't want to marry you, give it
to me anyway'? So אמר רב חמא Amar Rav Chama כל הבא
מהבא לאו כלום היא. kol hava me-hava lav klum hee.
No, so if you say it with a double לשון lashon הבא
מהבא, hava me-hava, it does not count.
ההוא גברא דהוה שתי חמרא בחנותא, hahu gavra dehavay shatey chamra be-chanuta,
there was a man who was drinking wine in the שוק. shuk.
אתאי ההיא איתתא, Atay hahi iteta, and
the woman came up to him. אמרה ליה, Amerah leh, הב לי
חד כסא, havli chad kasa, give me a cup of wine, one
cup of wine. אמר לה, Amar lah, אי יהיבנא ליך מיקדשת לי,
ee havinah lach mekudeshet lee, if I give it to you will
you be married to me? אמרה ליה, Amerah leh, אשקי אשקיין, ashkey
ashkayan,
just let me drink the wine, with a double לשון lashon again.
אמר רב חמא Amar Rav Chama כל אשקי אשקיין לאו כלום היא,
kol ashkey ashkayan lav klum hee, and if you say it with
a double לשון lashon it doesn't count. ההוא גברא דהוה קשדי תמרי
מדיקלא, hahu gavra dehavay kashadi tamrey midikla,
there was a man picking dates off of the tree and throwing
them down onto the ground. That's how they would harvest the dates.
אתאי ההיא איתתא, Atay hahi iteta, the woman came. אמרה ליה, Amerah
leh, שדי לי תרתי, shadi lee tartey, send me down, throw me
down two dates. Interesting why she says two dates and not one
date like the rest of the cases were one, each of the
thing one necklace, one cup of wine. Here it's two dates. Maybe
the price of dates was so low it had to be שוה
פרוטה. shaveh perutah.
Too hungry, one date wouldn't fill her up.
Or one date wouldn't fill her up. It's interesting what's the minimal
amount of food for eating on יום כיפורים Yom Kippurim that we
say is ככותבת הגסה, k'kotevet ha-gassa, a big a big כותבת. kotevet.
Okay, שדי לי תרתי. shadi lee tartey. אמר לה, Amar lah, אי
שדינא ליך מיקדשת לי, ee shadina lach mekudeshet lee, if
if I give it to you will you be married to me?
אמרה ליה, Amerah leh, שדי משדי, shadi mishadey,
throw it down to me. אמר רב זביד Amar Rav Zvid כל
שדי משדי לאו כלום היא, kol shadi mishadey lav klum hee, and
if you just say throw it down throw it down with a
double לשון lashon that does not count. איבעיא להו Iba'ya lehu הב
אשקי ושדי מהו? hav ashkey veshadey mahu?
So they ask back, if you say it with a single לשון,
lashon, exactly Michael's question, if you say with just a single לשון
lashon would that work? אמר רבינא Amar Ravina מקודשת. mekudeshet. רבינא Ravina
says yes. רב סמא בר רקתא Rav Sama bar Rakta אמר amar
תאגא דמלכא taga de-malka אינה מקודשת. eyna mekudeshet.
And it's a מחלוקת אמוראים machloket Amoraim because רב סמא בר רקתא
Rav Sama bar Rakta says I swear by the crown of the
king she's not married.
You don't see that too often.
You don't see it too often.
Usually they swear by God like you know.
For sure, they usually say חי אלקים. Chai Elokim. It's interesting to
note רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel that's quoted in the רשב"א Rashba says
תאגא דמלכא taga de-malka means even if she if he would have
given her תאגא דמלכא, taga de-malka, the crown of the king, such
a high value object, she wouldn't marry him in this context because
the way she's agreeing to it she's not really agreeing to it.
So but that's a
מחלוקת אמוראים.
machloket Amoraim. So why doesn't he... Like God, I
mean,
no
I don't know. It's the same thing. תאגא דמלכא. taga d'malka. I
don't know, if you live in a place with a king so
you swear by the king's, the king's crown just as much. Okay.
It's just very strange to say that every single time, right, every
time
you would say this very specific case, exactly. Every time. Right.
It is sort of strange but I think it's to point to
a more general understanding of the fact that in those contexts, that
is someone asks for something with no strings attached, man responds, 'oh
yeah, I'll do it if you marry me,' and she's refusing. That's
really the point. Okay, and now we end with הלכתא hilchasa for
all the סוגיות sugyos that we've just seen. והלכתא אינה מקודשת v'hilchasa
eina mekudeshet in the case of this case. והלכתא שיראי לא צריכי
שומא. v'hilchasa shirai lo tzrichi shuma. Remember we had a מחלוקת machlokes
between רבה Rabba and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said that a silk, a piece of silk that you use to
get married would require an assessment of its value and רבה Rabba
said no. והלכתא כרבי אליעזר. v'hilchasa k'Rabbi Eliezer. רש״י Rashi says, reminds
us of what we're talking about. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was talking
about the case where he said התקדשי לי במנה ונתן לה דינר.
itkadshi li b'maneh v'nasan lah dinar. That was yesterday. That is you
promise to pay 100 דינר dinar for the marriage and you only
gave her one, so she is מקודשת mekudeshet but you have to
pay the rest. And והלכתא כרבא אמר רב נחמן. v'hilchasa k'Rava amar
Rav Nachman. In the case of רבא אמר רב נחמן, Rava amar
Rav Nachman, that was talking about the case of the משכון, mashkon,
the man says I'm going to give you 100 דינר dinar and
he doesn't give her anything but he gives her his watch as
a collateral, and we said מנה אין כאן משכון אין כאן. maneh
ein kan mashkon ein kan. It's not קידושין kiddushin because neither the
משכון mashkon nor the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin were actually given to
her. Yes.
So if the הלכה halacha is that שיראי אינה צריכה שומא, shirai
einah tzricha shuma, then how come some people say like oh you
shouldn't use like the diamond ring under the חופה? chuppah?
Ah, תוספות. Tosfos.
So
this is our big תוספות Tosfos right here. והלכתא שיראי לא צריכי
שומא. v'hilchasa shirai lo tzrichi shuma. And the ר״י, Ri, exactly asks
that question, which is that we use a wedding ring, and the
ר״י Ri tries to distinguish between the notion of, if you look
down I think it's about 15 lines down or so in the
תוספות, Tosfos,
yes, right where the תוספות רי הזקן Tosfos Ri ha-Zaken is. ואומר
רבינו תם v'omer Rabbeinu Tam דאתי לאשמועינן דדווקא שיראי הוא דלא צריכי
שומא. d'asa l'ashmuinan d'davka shirai hu d'lo tzrichi shuma. It's just silk
that doesn't need assessment לפי ששומתן ידועה.
le-fi she-shumatan
yeduah. People are relatively familiar with the value of silk ואין רגילין
לטעות בו כל כך. v'ein regilin lito'os bo kol kach. People don't
make such big errors. אבל שאר דברים כגון אבנים טובות ומרגליות שיש
שאינם טובות אלא מעט. aval shaar devarim kegon avanim tovos u-margaliyos she-yesh
she-einam tovos ela meat. There are precious stones that really aren't such
precious stones. You could imagine a cubic zirconia or some kind of
a rock that was found on the street that was polished up
very nicely, would still look very nice in a ring.
Giving your wife a diamond ring under the חופה chuppah you know
it's expensive.
Okay, so this is exactly the objection that develops in תוספות. Tosfos.
This תוספות Tosfos is the source for the questioning the notion of
even though we say שיראי אינה צריכה שומא, shirai einah tzricha shuma,
nonetheless by other things which are even harder to know their value,
perhaps there's room to be worried about that even. And the fact
is even with the silk maybe you should say we should be
מחמיר machmir anyway even if it were technically,
well what's the problem with that? What's the problem? It's worth שוה
פרוטה shaveh prutah and under. Exactly.
But remember what, so רב יוסף's Rav Yosef position that the problem
of שוה כסף shaveh kesef is that it's not קץ, kayitz, that
is it's not well defined what portion or what piece of it
is actually worth the שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah by שוה פרוטה, shaveh
prutah, it can't be subdivided in a clear way. So you would
say if we don't פסקן pasken like רב יוסף Rav Yosef it
shouldn't be a problem at all. But of course תוספות Tosfos want
to bring us back in. Perhaps it has to do with the
symbolic value that has become attached to using a ring, especially in
אשכנזי Ashkenazi communities. That is a variety of nice symbolisms around using
a ring. A ring is a link in the chain going back
to רבקה אמנו Rivka Imeinu who used, got married with rings. It
goes back to the notion that a marriage is a wholeness between
two different people. There's a lot of symbolism that has become attached
to rings. And therefore, you know, part of this discussion here is
we use a ring but we use a plain ring. We don't
use a ring that has a stone in it. That's this תוספות.
Tosfos.
Okay, let's continue with the next
סוגיא sugya and this now for the time being at least we're
done with קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef and the גמרא Gemara asks תנו
רבנן בשטר כיצד. tanu rabbanan b'shtar keitzad. How do you get married
using a שטר קידושין? shtar kiddushin?
I still just want to make sure I understood it though. Yeah.
So, so the issue is, even though it's worth quite a lot
of money, so you're saying that she, and everyone knows at least
that the ring and/or and the diamond in it or whatever it
is, is worth at least a פרוטה, prutah, so nevertheless but what?
She's thinking it's worth more?
So that's the later, that's the notion that's introduced later. Again it's
not actually what רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, but the notion that
if it's something that's worth significantly less than what she thinks it's
worth, even if it's still worth more than a פרוטה, prutah, the
woman would come back and say I only accepted it on the
condition that it was worth XYZ. But you tell her under
the חופה, chuppah, all right, this is worth a פרוטה. prutah. It's
worth a פרוטה. prutah. Right.
So, and that's how we get around it in cases where we
need to. But you could, the recommendation... we're going to see other
סוגיות *sugyas* that talk about ways of getting marriage which are not
recommended but technically work and and it becomes more sticky. Like you
said, like I said yesterday, you know, people who learn מסכת קידושין
kiddushin. *Masechet Kiddushin* shouldn't go and get married right afterwards because you
get all sorts of crazy ideas in your
head. You should do it the right way. But if you want
to talk about, you know, in any case where a couple is
really heart set on using a certain ring, there are certainly ways
to make it work. I heard a case actually, it was one
of the rabbis who graduated from Chovevei a few years ago. He
said that he was מסדר קידושין kiddushin *mesader kiddushin* for his brother's
wedding, and his brother is kind of like a hippie, crunchy granola
type of person, and wanted to buy his wife for כסף קידושין
kesef kiddushin *kesef kiddushin* a new bicycle. A new bicycle is a
few hundred dollars. But he said like, come on, you want to
give her the bicycle as a gift, fine, but like we get
married with a ring. That's how we do it. So, just an
interesting thing to consider that frankly she would know how much the
bike cost, he bought it, it's really his, he's giving it to
her, it's real, but also sort of reinforces this sort of strange
kind of transactional aspect of the קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* rather than the
more sort of formalized idea of just a simple transfer.
So that's the problem תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says, but it's really not
a problem is what we're saying?
It's really not a problem, meaning fundamentally, if you ask me, bottom
of the day, you give something of value that's worth more than
a פרוטה *prutah* and you both agree and the עדים *edim* knew
about it and everybody knew about it, there can't be anything wrong
with that at a fundamental level.
But yet we make a problem.
We make a problem about it because we do things a certain
way. We could talk about that more later. Okay. תנו רבנן *tanu
rabanan*. בשטר כיצד *bishtar keitzad*? How do you use קידושי שטר shtar
*kiddushei shtar*? As Rabbi Linzer noted in the first שיעור *shiur*, קידושי
שטר shtar *kiddushei shtar* probably was never really practiced. So some of
these הלכות halachos *halachot* are not well developed. You'll see that the
שטר shtar. *shtar* סוגיא sugya *sugya* is relatively short. תנו רבנן *tanu
rabanan*. בשטר כיצד *bishtar keitzad*? How do you write a שטר קידושין
shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin*? כתב לו על הנייר או על החרס *katav
lo al haniyar o al hacheres*, אף על פי שאין בו שווה
פרוטה *af al pi she'ein bo shaveh prutah*. You write on either
a piece of paper or even an ostracon, a shard of pottery,
even a what? An ostracon. A piece of broken pottery that was
used for writing in the ancient Near East.
Is there a word for it?
There is. It's a nice Greek word. אף על פי שאין בו
שווה פרוטה *af al pi she'ein bo shaveh prutah*, even though it
is worth less than a פרוטה *prutah*. That is, you could use
a piece of חרס *cheres*, a totally worthless piece of broken pottery.
Even if it's a tree that's attached to the ground, right?
Ah, so a tree attached to the ground is a מחלוקת machlokes
ראשונים rishonim *machloket rishonim* because we know the מחלוקת machlokes *machloket* between
the בעל העיטור Ba'al Ha'itur *Ba'al HaIttur* and the רשב"א Rashba *Rashba*
about whether, how much do we equate שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar
kiddushin* with a גט get *get*. And so because a גט get
*get* cannot be written on מחובר *mechubar*, the בעל העיטור Ba'al HaIttur
*Ba'al HaIttur* also says that, no, because their מחלוקת machlokes *machloket* is
actually about כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin, *kesef kiddushin*. Actually they both agree
that a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin* could not be written
on מחובר *mechubar*. But let's go back and we'll see the היקש
hekesh. הוויה ליציאה *hekesh havayah leyetziah* in just a moment. So what
do you write on the שטר shtar *shtar*? בתך מקודשת לי bitcha
mekudeshet li *bitecha mekudeshet li*, בתך מאורסת לי bitcha me'ureset li *bitecha
me'ureset li*, בתך לי לאינתו bitcha li le'into *bitecha li le'intu*. Your
daughter is married to me, three different ways. Ah, so it's very
interesting that at least the first ברייתא braisa *braita* that's quoted is
written between the husband and the father. It's interesting to note the
ברייתא braisa *braita* that we had from the תוספתא *Tosefta* about כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin *kesef kiddushin*
focuses on the man and the woman interacting together. That is, when
the woman is an adult and getting married. And here we have
a notion of a child marriage, perhaps one was more preferable than
the other for either context, or perhaps it was just how the
ברייתא braisa *braita* was recorded. It's interesting to note. הרי זו מקודשת
mekudeshet *harei zo mekudeshet*. מתקיף matkif. לה רבי זירא *matkif lah Rabbi
Zeira*. Rabbi Zeira had a question, Rabbi Zeira bar Memel. הא לא
דמי האי שטרא לשטר זביני *ha lo dami hai shtar leh shtar
zvini*. This שטר shtar *shtar* that is שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar
kiddushin* is not similar to a שטר shtar *shtar* of sale. That
is, when you buy a piece of land, how do you write
the שטר shtar *shtar*? The owner of the שטר shtar *shtar* writes
שדי מכורה לך sadi mechura lach *sadi mechurah lach*. My field is
sold to you and he gives you the שטר shtar, *shtar* and
that's the way the קניין kinyan *kinyan* works. קניין שטר shtar. *kinyan
shtar* for buying a field.
He doesn't mention what it is, too, does he?
You could include all sorts of things besides that. So the point
is to note that the action of giving the שטר shtar *shtar*
in purchasing a field is that the owner transfers the שטר shtar.
*shtar* and that's a deed of ownership. That means whoever's holding the
שטר shtar. *shtar* owns the field. That makes sense. שטר קידושין shtar
kiddushin *shtar kiddushin*. You're gaining the title. Exactly. That's the way we
think about it now. That's the way they thought about it back
then. שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin* works very differently. שטר קידושין
shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin* is exchanged in a certain sense. That is,
we don't want to speak in such crude terms, but in a
certain sense, the woman or her father is transferring control in some
sense, is compared to the seller of the field, and nonetheless it's
the husband who writes the שטר shtar *shtar* and gives the שטר
shtar *shtar* as similar to the כסף kesef, קניין *kesef kinyan* for
כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin *kesef kiddushin* as well. So that directionality is
reversed between קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* and purchase. Interestingly enough, that highlights the
fact that what's actually being done here is not a woman being
sold along with a deed that tells you now you own this
woman. Obviously not. What's happening is very similar to כסף קידושין kesef
kiddushin *kesef kiddushin*. That is, there's some kind of an exchange. In
this case, the שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin* is a very
formalized technical process, that is, it doesn't even have any value. The
way it works is because it's written on it. הרי את מקודשת
לי harei at mekudeshet li and that's all it is. We saw
the מחלוקת machlokes between the first רש"י Rashi on דף ב עמוד
א daf beis amud alef and the רש"י Rashi in the רי"ף
Rif about whether you even need to say any words when you
give a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin, because perhaps the fact that the
words are written down in the שטר shtar already you don't need
to say anything or not. So that's an interesting discussion as well.
It's not even a סוגיא in both אותו ענין, oto inyan, it's
whether שטר shtar is an embodied form of the אמירה amira or
not. So by כסף, kesef, קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef you have to
say הרי את מקודשת לי בטבעת זו harei at mekudeshet li be-tabaat
zu with the שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin? perhaps you don't have to
say הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li because it already
says הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li in the שטר.
shtar. One other point is that the רשב"א Rashba objects to this
ברייתא braita and the רשב"א Rashba's says this ברייתא braita is written
in shorthand. Obviously you can't just write הרי את מקודשת לי harei
at mekudeshet li on a piece of pottery and give it to
a woman and that works for קידושין. kiddushin Why not? Because what
kind of a שטר shtar is that? A שטר shtar has the
date, a שטר shtar? has the names, a שטר shtar has the
place.
But wouldn't it be said with the שטר shtar with the מכר
mecher you'd usually have the money?
Okay, so the point, and the שטר מכר shtar mecher usually would
have all sorts of other things in it as well and a
divorce certainly. So the רשב"א Rashba objection is that, that is, שטר
קידושין shtar kiddushin must have the names particular, and the ריטב"א Ritva
disagrees and from many of the other ראשונים Rishonim as well it
sounds like it's a much more abstract notion of a שטר, shtar
that is, it's a piece of something that has the words written
on it and that's enough to make it a שטר. shtar It
doesn't have to be anything more than that. So let's just see.
Okay, so the difference between a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushins and a
שטר זביני, shtar zvini, התם מוכר כותב לו שדי מכורה לך hatam
mocher kotev lo sadi mechura lach in that case in purchasing a
field the seller writes שדי מכורה לך my field is sold to
you. הכא בעל כותב בתך מקודשת לי. hacha baal kotev bitcha mekudeshet
li. Here the husband writes your daughter is married to me.
So the directionality, how does that work? Why would it work?
Shouldn't it be the other way around?
Right, he's just saying I'm noting the fact that this is odd
to a certain extent, that is, if we compare... It's מתקיף. He's
challenging the notion of the ברייתא braita and רבא Rava defends it
very well. אמר רבא התם מעניינא דקרא והכא מעניינא דקרא. amar Rava
hatam me-inyana de-kra ve-hacha me-inyana de-kra. Each of them is based on
a פסוק pasuk so we're going to see. התם כתיב ומכר מאחוזתו.
hatam kesiv u-machar me-achuzato. So where you sell a piece of your
ancestral lands, במוכר תלא רחמנא. be-mocher tala rachmana.
The Torah cares in the case of selling land about the seller
of the field. Okay, הכא כתיב כי יקח. hacha kesiv ki yikach.
So if the husband is the one doing the marital act, so
בבעל תלא רחמנא be-baal tala rachmana we care about the husband's action.
So here it's the husband who writes the שטר shtar and there
it's the seller of the field who writes the שטר. shtar התם
נמי כתיב שדות בכסף יקנו. hatam nami kesiv sados be-kesef yiknu.
So the פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu interestingly enough we're quoting פסוקים
psukim from פרשת בהר Parshas Behar and we're quoting the הפטרה haftarah
from פרשת בהר. Parshas Behar. So כתיב שדות בכסף יקנו, kesiv sados
be-kesef yiknu, fields are bought with money. Interestingly of course that it
says with money and not with the שטר. Shtar The שטר shtar
is also mentioned in the הפטרה haftarah there as well. But here
it sounds like the buyer of the field has a certain standing
as well, a legal standing. So קרי ביה יקנו, kari bei yaknu,
not buy, you buy fields with money, actually you sell fields with
money, you read it with different vowels. מאי טעמא קרי ביה יקנו?
mai taama kari bei yaknu? Why should you read it as יקנו?
yaknu? משום דכתיב ומכר mishum de-kesiv u-machar
because we already had the notion from the פסוק pasuk in the
תורה Torah that says that you sell the field. הכא נמי קרי
ביה כי יוקח. hacha nami kari bei ki yukach. Maybe you should
say when a woman is is taken and not when a man
takes a wife. So and we this has to be rejected דכתיב
את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה de-kesiv es biti nasati la-ish ha-zeh because
that's based on the other פסוק pasuk we know from in the
case of מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra, that in מוציא שם
רע motzi shem ra the father defends his daughter and himself by
saying את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה. es biti nasati la-ish ha-zeh. It
sounds like it's the father who gives the daughter over rather than
the husband who takes the daughter. And so this is left unresolved.
אלא אמר רבא הלכתא נינהו, ela amar Rava hilchasa ninhu, it's הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai ואסמכינהו רבנן
אקרא ve-asmachinhu rabbanan a-kra and they're just connected to the פסוקים psukim
later as a mnemonic but actually it's הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Le-Moshe
Mi-Sinai. תוספות Tosafos has a problem, תוספות Tosafos says it can't be
that both are הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai because of course
the פסוק pasuk for buying a field works perfectly. So תוספות Tosafot
says it's only the שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin the directionality of שטר
קידושין shtar kiddushin is learned out הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai.
Interesting to note remember the רמב"ם's Rambam's classification of what is הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai different from פירושים המקובלים מפי משה רבינו
perushim ha-mekubalim mi-pi Moshe Rabbeinu is that the quality of הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai means it's something which a person could never
figure out by by reading the פסוקים psukim and using deductive powers,
that is, for the most part entirely arbitrary הלכה. halacha. The fact
that the minimal size for eating is a כזית kezayis is הלכה
למשה מסיני, Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai, the size of ארבעים סאה arba'im se'ah
for a מקוה mikveh is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai things
like that rather than something that you could eventually figure out like
פרי עץ הדר pri etz hadar is an אתרוג esrog is פירושים
המקובלים מפי משה רבינו, perushim ha-mekubalim mi-pi Moshe Rabbeinu, if it were
lost there would be a way to figure it out rather than
הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai. So that's just an interesting...
The whole idea of using a שטר shtar, is הלכה למשה?
Halacha Le-Moshe? No remember we saw that the notion of using a
שטר shtar is learned out from היקש. hekesh? The problem is how
do we know who writes the שטר shtar is it the the
seller so to speak or... the buyer who writes the שטר. shtar,
I hate to use such crude terms, it's just more convenient than
speaking circuitously. Okay. ואיבעית אימא התם נמי כתיב Ve'iba'it eima hatam nami
ketiv ואקח את ספר המקנה. va'ekach et sefer hamiknah.
So what about the פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu that says, "I
took the book of sale," that is the person who in this
case it was ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, ירמיהו Yirmiyahu took the—he was buying his
uncle's field.
חמוּאל, Hamu'el, this is חנמאל. Hanam'el.
ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is buying his uncle's field in ענתות. Anatot. It's interesting
of course ירמיהו's Yirmiyahu whole life story, he grew up in the
countryside and he goes to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So he has to—part of
this whole נבואה nevuah was he goes back to his countryside home
to ענתות Anatot and he's there and his uncle is selling this
field and ירמיהו Yirmiyahu publicly buys the field to demonstrate, "Don't worry,
people shouldn't be selling their property in fear that they're going to
be exiled and they'll never come back. Rather, people should hold on
to their property or keep it in the family at least in
order to demonstrate yes, there will be an exile but we're coming
back." So it's a very important message of hope at the time
of the—at the time of the first חורבן. churban. ואמר רב עמרם
אמר רב נחמן V'amar Rav Amram amar Rav Nachman כתב לה על
הנייר או על החרס אף על פי שאין בו שוה פרוטה katav
lah al haniyar o al hacheres af al pi she'ein bo shaveh
prutah בתך מקודשת mekudeshet לי בתך מאורסת לי בתך לי לאינתו בין
על ידי אביה בין על ידי עצמה bein al yedei aviha bein
al yedei atzmah מקודשת
מדעתו. mida'ato. So if the—and this is a case of a girl
who is less than twelve years old, if he wrote on the
שטר shtar? "your daughter is married to me" and then he gave
that שטר shtar either to the daughter who's less than twelve years
old or to her father, it sounds like that would work for
קידושין kiddushin? מדעתו mida'ato with the father's דעת. da'at. That is, as
we saw תוספות a few דפים dafim ago already notes the fact
that when a father's marrying off his minor daughter, the דעת, da'at,
the primary legal standing is the father's and it's not somehow that
the father is a stand-in for his daughter, it's actually a totally
different mechanism of קידושין kiddushin, that goes through the father. Okay. So
it has to be with his דעת. da'at. והוא שלא בגרה Vehu
shelo bagra כתב לה על הנייר או על החרס katav lah al
haniyar o al hacheres אף על פי שאין בו שוה פרוטה af
al pi she'ein bo shaveh prutah הרי את מקודשת לי harei at
mekudeshet li, הרי את לי לאינתו harei at li le'into הרי את
מאורסת לי. harei at me'ureset li.
If he writes "you are married to me," בין על ידי אביה
בין על ידי עצמה bein al yedei aviha bein al yedei atzmah
then he gives it to her or he gives it to her
father מדעתה mida'atah with her consent, with her will, והוא שבגרה vehu
shebagra and that's in the case where she has come of age,
that is she's older than twelve and a half. We know that
between the age of twelve and twelve and a half, both of
them could accept קידושין. kiddushin Interesting,
let's pause for a moment and note the fact that this text
is problematic because it sounds like the father could accept קידושין kiddushin
for her after she's become בוגרת, bogeret, that is after the age
of twelve and a half, and other sources, other ברייתות braitot in
this גמרא Gemara note that that would not work. So all the
ראשונים Rishonim here note that this means, obviously, it must be that
מדעתה mida'atah means that she has appointed her father to be a
שליח קבלה shaliach kabbalah on her behalf. Otherwise if she had not
appointed him to be a שליח, shaliach, it wouldn't work.
What's the next thing to
say? המשיכו. Hamshichu.
We're going to get to—the שידוכים shidduchim is going to come up
on the next עמוד. amud. Yeah.
Part of the discussion there is going to come up very soon.
So we're just going to get through the next part. And this
yeah.
So but what I find interesting is sort of you said, "Okay,
so going back to the יקח וקח yikach ukach that whole thing."
Yeah. And the בקיחת המכפלה. b'kichat Hamachpelah. No, no, no, and then
really it's ואקח את ספר המקנה. va'ekach et sefer hamiknah. So does
that mean that no, then really it's based on פסוקים psukim and—but
that was ואיבעית אימא.
ve'iba'it eima. So how do you read ואיבעית אימא ve'iba'it eima when
the notion of using פסוקים psukim has been rejected? Perhaps you'll say,
"Yeah, really we just say it's ואקח את ספר המקנה, va'ekach et
sefer hamiknah, it depends on the גרסא, girsa, it depends on who
you read like, it's more complicated."
But it's a very interesting paradigm. It is. Either פסוקים psukim and
it's like דאורייתא d'oraisa almost—don't know—or no, no, it's an אסמכתא.
asmachta. That's true. Certainly true. It's polar opposites for sure. 100%. Also
quoting a פסוק pasuk from כתובים Ketuvim kind of puts you into
that אסמכתא asmachta category automatically almost, that is we don't really learn
הלכה halacha from נביאים Nevi'im and כתובים Ketuvim so much. Whenever we're
learning הלכה halacha from נביאים Nevi'im and כתובים, Ketuvim, often at least
there are some ראשונים Rishonim. who say this, like look, it's an
אסמכתא, asmachta, it's always going to be an אסמכתא asmachta if it's
נביאים Nevi'im and כתובים. Ketuvim. נביאים Nevi'im and כתובים Ketuvim aren't sources
of law in the same way, right? A later נביא navi besides
משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu comes up and tries to tell you the
הלכה. halacha. If he's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham he can tell
you הלכה halacha because he's a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. There's an
extensive discussion in the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam says fine, most
of the נביאים Nevi'im were also on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in their
time, but it doesn't mean
that the נבואה nevuah has a legal power in any sense.
It's just
a story.
It's a story about buying something. So it's informative in a sense
of how do you buy a field?
Right. Exactly. Right. He's telling you what does it mean for me
at a time of exile to be buying a field? Right.
Exactly. Right. It's worth looking into that part of ירמיהו Yirmiyahu I
find—ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is worth reading through. Okay. בעא רבי שמעון בן לקיש
Ba'ei Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish and now he's going to get introduced
to a מחלוקת machlokes, which is going to come up again on
דף מ"ד Daf Mem Dalet in about a month, which is מחלוקת
machlokes, between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about
how much do we say
היקש? הויה ליציאה. hekesh havayah l'yetziah. That is, how much do we
connect the process of marriage to the process of divorce, or would
we rather compare process of marriage to other mechanisms of marriage? That
is, is שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin more similar to כסף קידושין kesef
kiddushin, or is שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin. more similar to a שטר
גירושין? shtar gerushin? That is again, that's our question. To what is
it most similar? Is it most similar to the process of getting
divorced using a שטר? shtar It's the same object to a certain
extent. Or is it a process of getting married, and that's what
it should be compared to? So bei ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
it was
also discussed by the דבי אביי de-bei Abaye as well. It's going
to be a major theme throughout the מסכתא masechta to a certain
extent, which is when we and that has major implications for understanding
גירושין. gerushin. Is גירושין gerushin an unraveling or an undoing of קידושין?
kiddushin Is it the opposite of קידושין, kiddushin, or is it some
new process? Right? Remember that when a woman gets divorced, it's not
a revert she doesn't revert back to her pre-marital state. She has
a halachic status as someone who has been divorced. That means it
was a transfer from stage one, stage two, and now to stage
three. It's not really going back to stage one when she gets
divorced.
In some ways it is in terms of תרומה, terumah, I think,
if she's an
Well, in terms of תרומה, terumah, yes, but in terms of being
able to marry a כהן, kohen, no. So there are certain important
נפקא מינות nafka minas there about what it means to be divorced.
So bei רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish asked, שטר אירוסין שכתבו שלא לשמה, shtar eirusin she-katavo shelo
lishma, what if you wrote a שטר אירוסין, shtar eirusin, a שטר
קידושין, shtar kiddushin not לשמה? lishma? We know that a גט get,
has to be written לשמה. lishma. It has to be written for
the sake of this particular woman to get divorced, obviously. And that's
part of how we know that the גט get? needs to have
the names as well, and it has to have a certain explicit
intent on the part of the סופר sofer and all sorts of
other things. So what about שטר קידושין? shtar kiddushin? שטר קידושין shtar
kiddushin. already sounds somehow much more informal than a גט, get just
the way the גמרא Gemara has been describing it. So שטר אירוסין
שכתבו שלא לשמה, shtar eirusin she-katavo shelo lishma, מהו? mahu?
Which means what?
Which means is it more similar to כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin which
of course doesn't need any לשמה lishma at all? Or does it
need to be לשמה lishma just like a גט?
get That is you don't mean that like you wrote it for
I wrote it for you didn't put in a name.
You don't put the name, you just you're the סופר sofer and
you just sit there writing הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet
li, הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, הרי את מקודשת
לי, fifty שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin and you sell them for sale
in your סופר sofer's shop and everyone comes and buys a שטר
קידושין shtar kiddushin. that wasn't written לשמה. lishma. That's what it is,
right?
So like if you put like the משלוח מנות mishloach manos but
don't say who
it's for, or give something like that. Okay. מהו? mahu? הויה ליציאה
מקשינן? havayah l'yetziah makshinan? Do we make a היקש hekesh between הויה
ליציאה, havayah l'yetziah. that is between marriage and divorce? מה יציאה בעינן
לשמה, mah yetziah ba'inan lishma, just like a גט get requires לשמה,
lishma, אף הויה בעינן לשמה, af havayah ba'inan lishma, so too marriage
or שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin, particularly should require to be written לשמה.
lishma. או דילמא, o dilma, maybe, הויה להדדי מקשינן, havayah l'hadadi makshinan,
we connect different processes of marriage to each other. מה הויה דכסף
לא בעינן לשמה, mah havayah d'kesef lo ba'inan lishma, money that is
used for marriage does not need to be לשמה. lishma. How could
you make money לשמה lishma anyway? Would you mint the coins לשם
קידושין? leshem kiddushin? It doesn't even make sense really to discuss. So
כסף לא בעינן לשמה, kesef lo ba'inan lishma, אף הויה דשטר לא
בעינן לשמה. af havayah d'shtar lo ba'inan lishma. So too the שטר
קידושין shtar kiddushin, would not need to be written לשמה. lishma. בתר
דבעיא הדר פשטה. basar de-ba'ya, hatar pash-ta. After he asked the question,
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish answered his own question. הויה ליציאה מקשינן. havayah
l'yetziah makshinan. And we see that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is very
much the champion of the notion היקש הויה ליציאה. hekesh havayah l'yetziah,
קידושין kiddushin. and גירושין gerushin are intrinsically, deeply connected and we learn
many הלכות halachas one from the other. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to
a certain extent is going to reject that on דף מ"ד. daf
mem dalet. But ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, הויה ליציאה מקשינן, havayah
l'yetziah makshinan, דאמר קרא, de-amar kra, ויצאה והיתה. v'yatz'a v'hay'ta. The גמרא
Gemara in מ"ד mem dalet has a colorful story. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had this מחלוקת machlokes and someone
was absent, now I forget which of the אמוראים Amoraim wasn't there,
but he comes back and says so what happened in the בית
מדרש Beis Medrash today? And he says oh, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had a מחלוקת, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and all of the חכמים chachamim said we don't hold by
היקש הויה ליציאה, hekesh havayah l'yetziah, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish got
up and started screaming, צווח ככרוכיא, tavech k'kruchiya, he was squawking like
a goose, הויה ליציאה, havayah l'yetziah, הויה ליציאה, havayah l'yetziah, הויה ליציאה.
havayah l'yetziah, So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish very much invested in this
notion of marriage and divorce, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan much less
so.
But so he's the only one that's quoted here, so that means
right,
so this גמרא Gemara we פוסקין pasken at least in this הלכה,
halacha, it sounds like we פוסקין pasken by ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
Later on, there's going to be another case where we don't take
it so far. Everyone agrees to the notion of היקש הויה ליציאה,
hekesh havayah l'yetziah obviously to a certain extent that's how we learn
the entire institution of שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin. The question is then
how much does it have to be similar to a גט get,
or not?
So it means you have to put in the date and the
names.
Well, or not. Or does it need to be לשמה lishma or
not? And that's this רשב"א Rashba, and ריטב"א Ritva מחלוקת, or and
that's a מחלוקת between the בעל העיטור and the רשב"א, all of
these other questions about how connected is a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin
to שטר אירוסין shtar eirusin or not is exactly related to this
question: is היקש hekesh. הויה ליציאה havayah l'yetziah. a full equation or
not? And again, because none of this was ever really הלכה למעשה,
halacha le-ma'aseh, it never really got פוסקין paskened in a solid way,
how are we really פוסקין paskening in terms of a שטר קידושין?
shtar kiddushin, Because no one uses a שטר קידושין.
shtar kiddushin If someone were to use a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin
today, where would it
would be problematic because a lot of these הלכות are not fully
fleshed out in the so does
it make you קדוש kadosh again
if you give look, ah, so this is important and now we
have to take a look, which is if we take a look
in the ראשונים. If anyone has a רי"ף, Rif, it's very important,
it's one line, so if you don't have a רי"ף Rif you
don't have to, but if you take a look in your רי"ף
Rif on page, it's, I think it's on ב' עמוד ב'. bet
amud bet. No, א' עמוד ב'. alef amud bet. א' עמוד ב'
alef amud bet in the רי"ף Rif where he's talking about what
does it mean בשטר מנלן דכתיב ויצאה והיתה מקיש הויה ליציאה מה
יציאה בשטר אף הויה בשטר ירושלמי הדא דתימא בשטר שאין בו שוה
פרוטה. bishtar minalan dechsiv v'yatza v'haysa makish havaya l'yitzia mah yitzia bishtar
af havaya bishtar Yerushalmi hada d'teima bishtar she'ein bo shaveh pruta. The
ירושלמי Yerushalmi says we're talking about only a שטר shtar that is
itself not worth שוה פרוטה, shaveh pruta, אבל אם יש בו שוה
פרוטה כסף הוא. aval im yesh bo shaveh pruta kesef hu. As
soon as a שטר shtar is actually worth a שוה פרוטה, shaveh
pruta, which is not very much anyway, if the שטר shtar. has
a value, it works as כסף קידושין kiddushin. even if you're trying
to use it as שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin, That's what it sounds
like from that ירושלמי Yerushalmi and the רי"ף Rif פסקנס paskens by
it. So the נפקא מינה nafka mina is very narrow. That is,
if you are using דווקא davka a שטר shtar. which you think
is a כשר kosher שטר shtar which somebody else probably thinks is
a פסול pasul שטר shtar, and there is less than שוה פרוטה.
shaveh pruta. That's the only way where we would have a problem
of using a שטר קידושין, shtar kiddushin which would be very rare
anyway. The שטר קידושין, shtar kiddushin. if it's written on a nice
piece of paper,
whatever, or you hire the סופר sofer to write it, it's worth
more than a שוה פרוטה. shaveh pruta. It looks nice, you're done,
right? It's worth שוה פרוטה, shaveh pruta, it's going to work as
כסף קידושין anyway.
Suppose you got like one of these looseleaf papers.
A looseleaf paper, even one slice of looseleaf paper, I don't know,
it's pretty close, I don't know.
What are you going to do with it?
I mean, like, what are you going to do with it? It's
a good question. Look, that's part of the question. That's why the
whole intrinsic value of שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin שטר shtar doesn't have
הנאה. hana'ah. We saw, right, ביאה bi'ah and כסף, הנאתן מרובה, hana'asan
merubah, they have הנאה hana'ah involved, and שטר shtar does not. And
that's part of it. רבי אלחנן ואסרמן Rebbe Elchonon Wasserman has a
point about the who writes the שטר, shtar, to note also that
part of the question is who is the major actor here? Are
we talking about the מתחייב, mischayev, the person who is obligating themselves
in an obligation through which this process takes place? That's the woman
in this case, right? Do you need to write the שטר shtar.
עם דעת המתחייב im da'as hamischayev or do you need to write
the שטר with דעת בעל השטר? da'as ba'al hashtar? Who's the one
writing the שטר, giving the שטר? So because of the role reversal
with שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin? that we saw, that it's the husband
who writes the שטר and not the woman or her father, then
there's a bit of a bifurcation of the roles of the מתחייב
mischayev and the בעל השטר ba'al hashtar that causes some interesting questions
to come up. So let's take a look here, the next
part. איתמר כתבו לשמה ושלא מדעתה. Ismar: kesavo lishma v'shelo mada'atah. What
if it was written לשמה, lishma, this is talking in this case
about a שטר קידושין, if it was written לשמה ושלא מדעתה, lishma
v'shelo mada'atah, it was not written with her knowledge or her consent.
רבא ורבינא אמרי מקודשת. Rava v'Ravina amri mekudeshes.
Hey, we just had that before. I mean ע"א עמוד א'. ayen
alef amud alef. You give it to the father, he gives it
to her.
Okay, so but we said it works if it was מדעתה, mida'atah,
it works if she agrees to accept it. What if she did
not know about this שטר yet? She only will agree to it
by the time it comes into her hand, but the husband went
and secretly wrote the שטר without asking her first. And now he
has a שטר that was written שלא מדעתה, shelo mada'atah, it was
written without her consent, and he comes to give it to her,
and when she accepts it, she accepts it with consent.
Except that we said this, we said if it's מדעתה mida'atah then
whatever.
No, מדעתה mida'atah there they're talking about accepting the שטר. Here we're
talking about writing the שטר. Was the שטר written with or without
her consent? So if she did not consent or did not even
know about the writing of the שטר, that's the question. רבא ורבינא
אמרי מקודשת. Rava v'Ravina amri mekudeshes. Rava and Ravina say it does
work. רב פפא ורב שרביא אמרי אינה מקודשת. Rav Papa v'Rav Sharvya
amri einah mekudeshes. So we have
מחלוקת אמוראים. machlokes Amoraim. אמר רב פפא אימא טעמא דידהו ואימא טעמא
דידי. Amar Rav Papa: eima ta'ama didhu v'eima ta'ama didi. I'm going
to tell you the reason for your own שיטה shittah and I'm
going to tell you the reason why I'm right. אימא טעמא דידהו,
Eima ta'ama didhu, I'm going to tell you your reason first. דכתיב
ויצאה והיתה מקיש הויה ליציאה. Dechsiv v'yatza v'haysa makish havaya l'yitzia. You
think it's because of the היקש. That is, we connect שטר קידושין
to גירושין. geirushin. מה יציאה לשמה ושלא מדעתה, Mah yitzia lishma v'shelo
mada'atah, just like a גט can be written לשמה lishma as long
as it's written לשמה lishma it can be written against the woman's
will. She doesn't have to agree to get divorced. אף הויה נמי
לשמה ושלא מדעתה. Af havaya nami lishma v'shelo mada'atah. So too a
שטר קידושין could be written לשמה lishma for her, but without her
knowledge and without her consent. ואימא טעמא דידי, V'eima ta'ama didi, Rav
Papa says I'm going to tell you the reason why I think
you're wrong. It's the same thing. ויצאה והיתה מקיש הויה ליציאה. V'yatza
v'haysa makish havaya l'yitzia. We connect marriage to divorce. מה יציאה בעינן
דעת מקנה, Mah yitzia ba'inan da'as makneh, in the case of divorce
you need the husband's consent because he is the one who is
the seller, that is he's giving away his wife, he is מגרש
migaresh his wife. אף הויה בעינן דעת מקנה. Af havaya ba'inan da'as
makneh. So too in the case of marriage you need the דעת,
da'as, the consent, even to write the שטר from the one who's
doing the quote-unquote selling, which is either the woman or her father.
Not with money, though.
Not what do you mean about money?
Well, money, she doesn't have to know, she doesn't have to know
in advance that he's going to try to, you know, pop the
question.
Well, that's exactly the point, which is that כסף קידושין has no
connection to גירושין geirushin almost, right? When we're talking about שטר קידושין,
do we say שטר קידושין is connected to שטר גירושין? shtar geirushin?
That's the רשב"א'ס Rashba's שיטה. shittah. There is the בעל העיטור who
thinks that for the reason you couldn't use a piece of land
as כסף קידושין, would think that even כסף קידושין is connected in
some ways to גירושין, geirushin, but that's a very
minority. No one is writing a שטר קידושין. Okay, מיתיבי, meiteivei, אין
כותבים שטרי אירוסין ונישואין אלא מדעת שניהם. ein kotvim shtarei eirusin u-nisuin
ela mi-da'at sheneihem. And this we have even a ברייתא braita, that
says in support of רב פפא, Rav Pappa, you cannot write a
שטר קידושין or a שטר נישואין shtar nisuin which refers to the
כתובה, ketubah, except with the knowledge and consent of both parties. That
is monetary contracts generally, of course, you require the דעת da'at of
both parties involved. Okay, מאי לאו שטרי אירוסין ונישואין ממש? mai lav
shtarei eirusin u-nisuin mamash? Do you really think that ברייתא is talking
about שטר אירוסין shtar eirusin and שטר קידושין? This is a response.
This ברייתא doesn't support רב פפא, Rav Pappa, otherwise how could רבא
Rava and רבינא Ravina have had their שיטה shittah if there was
this ברייתא, right? So we have to reject the notion that there's
a תנאי Tannaic source in support of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. And
so we say מאי לאו שטרי אירוסין ונישואין ממש לא. mai lav
shtarei eirusin u-nisuin mamash lo.
שטרי פסיקתא.
shtarei
pasikta. We're talking about שטרי פסיקתא, shtarei pasikta, which are a שטר
written on the engagement, the terms of engagement, that is how much
people are promising to pay for the wedding or the dowry or
all sorts of things and this
is what we call תנאים tannaim these days.
That's what we would call a תנאים, tannaim, right? רש"י Rashi even
uses the word שטרי פסיקתא התנאים שביניהם וממון שפוסקין זה על זה.
shtarei pasikta ha-tannaim she-beineihem u-mammon she-porskin zeh al zeh. The conditions that
they've set up between them and the ממון mammon they are exchanging,
the different families, how much who's going to pay for the caterer,
who's going to pay for the flowers, who's going to pay for
this. So if they would write out a שטר, now it's important
to note as far as I understand, and I could be wrong
about this, but if I remember learning Rav Soloveitchik in particular was
very opposed to the practice of having the תנאים tannaim on the
day of the wedding. He says it makes no sense to make
a formal legal agreement for something that has already been agreed for
and paid for and dealt with already and is totally meaningless just
to have כיבודים kibbudim to give out at the wedding. So certainly
there are customs in some communities to write a שטר תנאים shtar
tannaim at the engagement party months before the wedding. But then what
if the engagement is broken off? You get into a situation where
you have a financial obligation between these parties.
Well, that's the whole
point of the תנאים tannaim though. Exactly. So that's part of the
complication, which is that in a case, you know, in a society
where our marriages are much less based on finances and much more
based on romance, already then you're in a sticky situation if the
romance fails, then what do you do with the finances if it's
really written in a שטר. So the תנאים tannaim is certainly a
nice thing looking back in retrospect, but it a certain- a certain
parts of it don't translate well to modern society. וכדרב גידל אמר
רב דאמר רב גידל אמר רב כמה את נותן לבנך כך וכך
לבתך כך וכך עמדו וקדשו קנו הן והן הדברים הנקנים באמירה. u-ke-di-Rav
Gidel amar Rav d'amar Rav Gidel amar Rav kama at noten le-vincha
kach ve-kach le-vitcha kach ve-kach amdu ve-kidshu kanu hen ve-hen ha-devarim ha-niknim
be-amirah.
So if the families make an agreement about the תנאים, tannaim, about
their engagement and dowry and things like that, I'm giving this much
for your son, I'm giving this much for your daughter, and then
if they get up and get married, that is the couple ends
up getting married, then the חלות chalot of those קניינים, kinyanim, verbal
agreements, even works verbally. That is the קניין made by the קידושין
works to cement the obligations made verbally. And that's why they say
הן והן הדברים הנקנים באמירה. hen ve-hen ha-devarim ha-niknim be-amirah. There are
very few things in הלכה halakhah where just saying it obligates you,
but this is one of them.
Okay, but nevertheless our case was writing it down.
Yes, but in other words this is just an extension to say
we know of such a concept as engagement agreements. Now it's interesting
to note as well in the גמרא Gemara times the קידושין probably
served a role much more similar to our engagement, that is it
was something done months in advance of the quote-unquote wedding celebration. But
because of the הלכה halakhic ramifications of קידושין, as is to break
it off would require a גט, you really are married at the
time of קידושין. So it became even a practice to have something
beforehand already by the time of רב. Rav. רב Rav made a
גזירה gezeirah against people who would get married without quote-unquote שידוכי. shidduchei.
Whatever שידוכי shidduchei is, it refers to some kind of agreement in
advance, it refers to some kind of conditions. So there's a lot
going on there as well. Let's try to make a little bit
more progress here, just don't want to leave so so much for
Rabbi Linzer to have to catch up tomorrow. Okay, בביאה. bi-viah. מנלן?
menalan? So how do you get married using ביאה, bi-viah, that is
through a sexual act between the man and the woman? This is
for קידושין. So מנלן? menalan? אמר רבי אבהו, amar Rabbi Abbahu, sorry,
where is it derived from? מנלן? menalan? אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן דאמר קרא בעולת בעל. amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Yochanan de-amar
k'ra be'ulat ba'al. In a discussion of נערה המאורסה, na'arah ha-me'orasah, that
is a woman who
was מקודשת but before she was נשואה. nisuah. So in that gap
which nowadays we don't have so much of a gap, but if
they had been months in between, if there was a woman who
was raped between the time of
קידושין ונישואין, kiddushin u-nisuin,
between קידושין ונישואין, kiddushin u-nisuin, sorry, and the punishment for that is
סקילה skilah rather than חנק. chenek. Normal sex with an אשת איש
eshet ish is punished by חנק, chenek, strangulation with the ropes, but
נערה המאורסה na'arah ha-me'orasah is punished with סקילה, skilah, stoning. So it's
a different, a different crime. It is worse so to speak. דאמר
קרא בעולת בעל מלמד שנעשית לו בעל על ידי בעילה. de-amar k'ra
be'ulat ba'al melamed she-na'asait lo ba'al al yedei be'ilah. It's that פסוק
pasuk teaches that he becomes her husband through sex. אמר ליה רבי
זירא לרבי אבהו ואמרי לה רבי לוי לריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. amar
leh Rabbi Zeira le-Rabbi Abbahu va-amri lah Rabbi Levi le-Resh Lakish le-Rabbi
Yochanan. כי
עובזא *ke'uvza* ששנה רבי *sheshana Rebbi*? Are you disagreeing? Do you think
it's so disgusting or wrong what רבי *Rebbi* said? ובעלה *U've'alah*, the
פסוק *pasuk* right, talking about marriage, not some פסוק *pasuk* about נערה
המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*. It says כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה *ki yikach
ish isha u've'alah*, so it says ובעלה *u've'alah*, מלמד שנקנית בביאה *melamed
shenikneit be'vi'ah*. That was from רבי *Rebbi*. רבי יהודה הנשיא *Rabbi Yehudah
HaNasi* said that. So why are you disagreeing with him? אי מהתם
*ee meihatam*, הוה אמינא *hava amina* עד דמקדש והדר בעיל *ad demikadesh
v'hadar be'il*. If I had learned it just from the פסוק *pasuk*
about קידושין *kiddushin*, I would have thought you need to do קידושין
*kiddushin* and then have sex just to reach the stage of קידושין
*kiddushin*. That is what? That is because it says כי יקח איש
אשה ובעלה *ki yikach ish isha u've'alah*. You do both actions. You
give her כסף *kesef* or שטר *shtar* and you have sex. So
that wouldn't work. That's not what we learn. קא משמע לן *ka
mashma lan*.
And that's why we need to also have the פסוק *pasuk* בבעולת
בעל *bi'vulat ba'al*.
How do you know that's not just נישואין *nisuin* though, בבעולת בעל
*bi'vulat ba'al*? Okay, נו *nu*. So they're going to have to
have some דרשה *drasha* words about this.
Okay. מתקיף לה רבי אבא בר ממל *matkif lah Rabbi Abba bar
Memel*. בבעולת בעל *be'ulat ba'al* meaning the woman... well, because it's about
a נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*, which is a case that we know
is before... והיא... *v'hi...* well, what does the פסוק *pasuk*
says, מאורסה לאיש ולא...
*me'orasah l'ish v'lo...* and I forgot the פסוק *pasuk*. I'm sorry.
Is there a חומש *Chumash*?
Anyway, נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*. Right. Right, we have to make...
yeah, it's the בבעולת בעל *bi'vulat ba'al*
meaning that it's a woman והיא בעולת בעל *v'hi be'ulat ba'al*. Right.
With her... with the actual husband. Right. And then the rapist is
the second.
Right. And then that's considered to just be a rape of a
married woman and not נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*. Right. Okay, let's keep
going. Sorry. So קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*. מתקיף לה רבי
אבא בר ממל *matkif lah Rabbi Abba bar Memel*. אם כן *im
kein*, נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah* דאמר רחמנא בסקילה *de'amar Rachmana b'skilah*. If
so, if you're going to tell me that you would have had
that הוה אמינא *hava amina* that needed to be rejected, that was
the הוה אמינא *hava amina* that you need to first do what
we would call קידושין *kiddushin* and you need to have sex in
order for it to be קידושין *kiddushin*. How would you ever have
a case of נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah* from the תורה *Torah* that
תורה *Torah* gave a special punishment of סקילה *skilah* rather than אשת
איש *eishet ish* which is punished with חנק *chenek*? היכי משכחת לה
*heichi mishkachat lah*? How would you have such a case? אי דאקדש
והדר בעיל *ei d'akdesh v'hadar be'il*. If he would have done קידושין
*kiddushin* and then had sex, בעולה היא *be'ulah hi*. Then she's no
longer a virgin. She's had sex already. So the punishment would be
חנק *chenek* anyway. אי דאקדש ולא בעיל *ei d'akdesh v'lo be'il*. And
if you had done קידושין *kiddushin*
but not had sex, לאו כלום הוא *lav klum hu*. Then that's
also nothing because she's not even מאורסה *me'orasah* yet.
Okay. But בבעולת בעל *bi'vulat ba'al* is not by ארוסה *arusah*. You
mean to say איש השוכב עם אשה בעולת בעל ומתו גם שניהם
*ish hashocheiv im isha be'ulat ba'al umetu gam sheneihem*? It's a regular
rape case. That's the right... that's the point is that בבעולת בעל
*be'ulat ba'al* is referring to a normal case, normal case of rape.
בקידושין *bikiddushin* though? But that's the point is that בבעולת... anyway, the
point is to say that בבעולת בעל *be'ulat ba'al*, he becomes her
בעל *ba'al* through ביאה *bi'ah*. Okay. ואמרו רבנן קמיה דאביי *v'amru rabanan
kamei d'Abaye*. משכחת לה כגון שבא עליה ארוס שלא כדרכה *mishkachat lah
k'gon she'ba aleha arus shelo k'darkah*. What if they had had anal
sex for the sexual act of קידושין *kiddushin* and thus she would
still be physically considered to be a virgin and thus she would
be allowed, she would be able to be considered נערה המאורסה *na'arah
hame'orasah* afterwards? Okay. אמר ליה אביי *amar leh Abaye*. עד כאן לא
פליגי רבי ורבנן אלא באחר *ad kan lo pligi Rebbi v'rabanan ela
b'acher*. It's only if another person had had intercourse with her. אבל
בעל דברי הכל אם בא עליה שלא כדרכה עשאה בעולה *aval ba'al
divrei hakol im ba aleha shelo k'darkah as'ah be'ulah*. Everyone agrees that
if the husband has anal sex with her, even though in a
certain sense physiologically she would still be quote unquote a virgin from
their perspective about discussing hymenal bleeding and things like that, but nonetheless
they would consider that the husband having a marital act of sex
renders her בעולה *be'ulah* whether it is anal sex or vaginal sex.
מאי היא דתניא *mai hi detanya*. באו עליה עשרה אנשים ועדיין היא
בתולה *ba'u aleha asarah anashim v'adayin hi betulah*. How do we deal
then with the case from סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, if ten men raped a
woman and she could still be a virgin afterwards? כולם בסקילה *kulam
b'skilah*. That is they are all punished with stoning. רבי אומר אומר
אני הראשון בסקילה וכולן בחנק *Rebbi omer omer ani harishon b'skilah v'kulan
b'chenek*. So רבי *Rebbi* disagrees because רבי *Rebbi* says no, even if
it were by anal sex, the first case would be נערה המאורסה
*na'arah hame'orasah*, afterwards she would be considered to be a בעולה *be'ulah*
and then all the rest would be punishable by חנק *chenek*. That
is she's no longer considered to be a virgin at that case
after having had anal sex in even a case of rape. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק *amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*. משכחת לה כגון
שקידש בשטר *mishkachat lah k'gon she'kideish b'shtar*. No. What about the alternative
case? What if we were thinking you needed כסף *kesef* plus ביאה
*bi'ah* in order to reach קידושין *kiddushin*? But a שטר *shtar*? Oh,
well a שטר *shtar* is strong enough to work on its own.
It wouldn't need ביאה *bi'ah* at all. And therefore you could have
a case of נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah* and not have to deal
with any of this discussion here that we've just had about how
much, what kind of sexual act would or would not work for
קידושין *kiddushin* in order to create a case of נערה המאורסה *na'arah
hame'orasah*. If you give a שטר קידושין *shtar kiddushin*, then she would
be מאורסת *me'ureset* one hundred percent just with the שטר *shtar*, and
then if someone would rape her at that point, it would be
נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*. I'm sorry, wait.
So we was saying that ביאה *bi'ah* would make... what do we...
the problem is that the הלכה
*halacha* of נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*, that is punishable with סקילה *skilah*,
only applies if she is a virgin. So how could you have
a case where a woman was married to one man and then
raped by another man... No the answer was oh what about anal
sex? And we said no that's a מחלוקת תנאים *machlokes tanaim* about
whether or not an act of anal sex by the husband would
count to make her בעולה *be'ulah* or not. And the question then
was to say ah so we have a different suggestion that is
how could she be married without having had sex at all? Answer
שטר *shtar*. That is even within this הוה אמינא *hava amina* that
you might have thought כסף *kesef* plus ביאה *bi'ah* which needed to
be rejected by quoting the other פסוק *pasuk* בעולת בעל *be'ulas ba'al*.
It's a very convoluted סוגיא *sugya* but I think we're at a
good place with it right here. Let's just try to make a
little bit more progress because I know the מנין *minyan* is soon.
So קדושין בשטר *kiddushin beshtar* הואיל וגומר ומוציא *ho'il vegomer umotzi* just
like a שטר *shtar* can complete the entire act of divorce on
its own גומר ומכניס *gomer umachnis* then it can also create the
entire חלות *chalos* of קדושין *kiddushin* as well. ורבי יוחנן *verabi yochanan*
האי ובעלה *hai uva'alah* מאי עביד ליה *mai avid leih*? So what
does Rabbi Yochanan do with the פסוק *pasuk* ובעלה *uva'alah*? That is
once he says you learn it out all from בעולת בעל *be'ulas
ba'al* so מאי עביד ליה *mai avid leih*? ההוא מיבעי ליה *hahu
mibai leih* זו נקנית בביאה ואין אמה העבריה נקנית בביאה *zu nikneis
bevi'ah ve'ein amah ha'ivriyah nikneis bevi'ah*. He uses it to learn the
fact that a wife could be the קנין קדושין *kinyan kiddushin* could
be accomplished through sex but not אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah* that is
when a father gives over his daughter as an indentured servant for
a few years. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka daitach amina* תיתי בקל וחומר
מיבמה *tisei bekal vachomer miyevamah*. You might have learned it by קל
וחומר *kal vachomer* from יבמה *yevamah*. מה יבמה שאין נקנית בכסף נקנית
בביאה *mah yevamah she'ein nikneis bechesef nikneis bevi'ah*. יבמה *yevamah* cannot be
the קנין *kinyan* for יבמה *yevamah* cannot be established effectively through money
but it could be effected through an act of sex. זו שנקנית
בכסף אינו דין שנקנית בביאה *zu shenikneis bechesef eino din shenikneis bevi'ah*.
So an אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah* who is acquired through money should
she not also be able to be acquired through sex? מה ליבמה
שכן זקוקה ועומדת *mah leyevamah sheken zekukah ve'omedes*. No there's a difference
between יבמה *yevamah* and אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah* because יבמה *yevamah* is
זקוקה ועומדת *zekukah ve'omedes* she has a different status already. סלקא דעתך
אמינא *salka daitach amina* הואיל וכתיב אם אחרת יקח לו *ho'il uchesiv
im acheres yikach lo* הקשה הכתוב לאחרת *hiksha hakatuv lacheres*. So by
אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah* the תורה *Torah* connects her to another woman
that is if the slave master or his son would marry another
wife ah so it sounds like אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah* is connected
to the notion of being a wife so they're connected. מה אחרת
מקניא בביאה אף אמה העבריה מקניא בביאה *mah acheres mikanya bevi'ah af
amah ha'ivriyah mikanya bevi'ah*. So you might have thought that just like
a wife could be acquired through a sexual act so too אמה
העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah*. קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan* and that's why
Rabbi Yochanan needed to have a special פסוק *pasuk* that is ובעלה
*uva'alah* to teach you that a marriage is effected through sex but
not the קנינים *kinyanim* of אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriyah*.